是否一個更加好看的人,就會是一個好人呢?
好與不好,其實都是一個很含糊的概念。
如果一件事情你覺得好,我也可能覺得不好。
在羅馬書的結尾,保羅對信徒說:「我願意你們在善上聰明,在惡上愚絕。」
善是如何去分好與不好呢?
如果大家想教會成為一個好的教會,保羅所說的「眾善」哪一種是好,究竟是指什麼呢?
我希望今天的信息幫助我們明白什麼叫做好,什麼叫做善。
讓我們的教會都成為一個好的教會。
我們低頭禱告。
請老天父,感謝祢今天帶我們來到祢的面前。
當我們去預備聆聽祢話語的時候,求祢幫助我們闖開我們的心靈,
取去一切讓我們分心的事,讓我們的心變得柔軟,能夠真正聽到祢的聲音。
求祢的話語清楚地向我們講話,讓我們不單止是聽見,也願意去實踐。
我們奉主耶穌基督的名求,阿們。
要去明白保羅口中所說的好,我們首先去明白羅馬教會。
今天經文滿有的人名,平時我們讀經的時候讀到這麼多人名,你可能會覺得為什麼要讀這麼多人名呢?讀他們有什麼用?
今天主席也刻意把全部的人名都讀一次,其實就是想大家去感受一下這個羅馬教會是怎樣由很多不同背景的人組成的一個教會。
首先,大家要知道羅馬教會其實不是保羅所創立的。
當保羅寫信給羅馬書的時候,其實他從來都沒有去過羅馬。
根據教會的傳統,主耶穌基督釘十字架之後,他們的門徒就開始四散。
有些由原本在羅馬住的猶太人,也在耶路撒冷信主之後返回到羅馬繼續生活,也有可能是在《仕途行傳》第八章所說到,
耶路撒冷教會面臨逼迫,信徒四散,有些人搬到羅馬那裡住。
換句話說,羅馬教會的出現並不是有人計劃建立的,而是信徒在不同的原因底下,自然地搬到羅馬,慢慢聚集起來。
當地也沒有一個牧師,也沒有一個使徒的領導,是由一班信徒一同去承擔教會的責任,互相去建立,互相去模仿。
教會有不同的背景的人去組成。
在第七節,安多尼古和尤尼亞被稱為保羅的親信,或者是猶太人。
在第九節,伊巴羅是拉丁文的名稱,羅馬人的背景,士大古是希臘文的名稱,羅馬教會是一個很大的種族用路。
在第三節講到的伯基拉和阿居拉是做帳篷生意的人。
在第八節講到的暗伯利是一個奴隸階層常見的名字,他可能是一個奴隸。
在第十一節講到的希羅天,大家提到希羅天可能想起是什麼人呢?
就是在福音書裡面希羅王,希羅家族的人。
在保羅時代有記載,一個王族秘書就叫做《約其數》,在羅馬教會裡面真的什麼人都有。
當時的羅馬教會不是一個教會,它是由多家的教會組成的。
第五節講到的伯基拉和阿居拉是做帳篷生意的人。
在第十一節講到的伯基拉和阿居拉是做帳篷生意的人。
在第五節講到的伯基拉和阿居拉是做帳篷生意的人。
根據考古墓碑的發現,有些信徒是住在北面貴族居住的馬爾思廣場區。
在十三章三節說道:「你只要行善,就可得到他的稱相。」
這裡說到他是一個掌權者,說到我們和政權之間的關係。
所以保羅所說的善不是抽象的東西,而是我們和神、人、仇敵、政權的關係處境所實踐出來的。
除了這些處境之外,保羅用羅馬教會的一些真實例子去展示我們什麼叫做好。
當時的羅馬教會有些信心軟弱的人,他們是不敢吃肉的,他們只吃菜。
他們覺得那些拜過偶像的肉是不潔淨的。
而另一班信徒,他們覺得什麼都可以吃的,所有東西都是屬於神,不需要潔淨。
所以他們彼此體諒就沒有問題了,但是那些人就經常去爭辯那些是好,那些是不好的。
保羅就說,這些什麼都吃的人就不要去看低一些不吃的人,不吃的人就不要去說那些吃的人不對。
他甚至會提出你究竟是誰,為什麼要去論斷主內的人呢?
問題的重點不是因為那個食物。
因為神的國在乎吃喝,在乎公義和平。
我想用今天一些例子來看,就是神的國不在乎今天你去哪裡喝茶,你用的廁紙夠不夠柔軟,或者唱你的詩歌是新歌還是舊歌呢?
保羅說不要再彼此論斷,因為這個「再」字是很重要的,是代表爭辯了一段時間,因為一些不重要的事情是破壞了神的工作。
例子講了這麼久之後,那究竟什麼是好呢?
牧師就想起一段講道,就是大概在他十七八歲的時候,可能不是很久以前的事情,因為那個講道的訊息一直在他的腦裏面。
他想起當時他們教會去經拜裏面的一些轉變。
當時的教會是由鋼琴去唱一些傳統的詩歌轉變,用到吉他,鼓,貝斯,或者電子琴。
牧師當時就這麼說:
當時有人提出質疑,牧師是不是因為他喜歡轉了這個敬拜的風格,是因為他喜歡夾Band?
但如果知道他熟悉的人,也知道牧師其實不夾Band的。
其實他就喜歡去拉二胡,
那可不可以因為我喜歡拉二胡,在這個音樂敬拜上去拉二胡呢?
或者我在敬拜裏面去拉二胡,彈琵琶,或者一些中樂。
去夾Band就是因為年輕人更加容易去接受,最重要不是一個音樂的形式,而是他們去敬拜的心。
We often think of good as a thing, a project, a plan, or a method.
Then we analyze it, compare, and look for the best solution.
But Paul's good isn't a thing, it's about how we live as a person.
It's something which we think is so good, hurt others, or cause someone to stumble, it is no longer that good.
In the book of Romans, good is not a program, it's not an event, it's not a budget, not even a product.
Paul's good is doing God's good will in our relationships. Being a good person who cares for others, builds others up, and loves one another, becoming such a person is truly good.
See in church, people talk a lot about evangelism. But if we always fight with little things, new believers may come and get scared and go.
So what is a good church? What is a good person in church?
Let Paul's conclusion in Romans 15 to be our conclusion.
We who are strong ought to bear the failings of the weak, and not to please ourselves. Each of us should please our labor for their good, to build them up.
這裏講到的堅強只是有能力,有空間的人願意去分擔沒有能力,沒有空間的人的乏力。
Reading it this way carries a sense of understanding and support.
這個分擔不是為了自己的喜悅而去證明自己。
Moreover, bearing others' failings isn't your own joy or to prove yourself. Look how great I am, how smart, how clever I am.
Bearing others' failings isn't about proving how capable we are, how capable I am, but to bring joy to the person we look after.
去分擔不是去證明自己有多能幹,而是去令對方得喜悅。為什麼他們會喜悅呢?
因為他們在無力的時候是有人得到陪伴和體諒。
Why would they feel joy? Because in their powerlessness, someone is there for them, someone understands them.
Bearing others' failings is meant to bring them benefit, that is, good.
To build them up so that they may later become someone who is able to take care of others.
分擔是為了叫人得益處,叫他們被就做,成為有能力去分擔其他人的軟弱。
See, this statement clearly explains what it means to be a good person who loves one another.
And also what a good church is. A church where people love one another is truly a good church.
這句話就清楚去講出了在乎他人的人是在乎他人的好人。
這裏講到好的教會裏面,人是在乎其他的人,這個就是一個好的教會。
I want to share a secret.
我想同大家分享一個秘密。
The book of Romans called Isaiah actually thirteen times.
在羅馬書中引用了以塞亞書很多次。
Isaiah is like a backbone of the book of Romans.
以塞亞書就是羅馬書的一個骨幹。
In Isaiah, last chapter,
以塞亞書最後一章Gory appears thirteen times.
榮耀講到了有十三次。
It talks about the people of all nations and languages, they will come and see God's glory
and to the distant islands that have not heard God's fame and seen God's glory.
They will proclaim my glory among the nations.
耶和華得榮耀豐盛的榮耀,列國的榮耀我的榮耀,漢建我的榮耀,我的榮耀存仰在列國。
In the last verse in Romans, it says,
在羅馬書最後幾節又這樣講,
May God give you the same attitude of might.
With one might and one voice, you may glorify God.
Accept one another in order to bring glory to God,
so that the Gentiles, the unbelievers, may glorify God.
願你們彼此同心,效法基督,一心一口榮耀神,
要彼此接納,使榮耀歸於神,叫外邦人因他憐憫而榮耀神。
Glory, glory and glory, one might and one voice brings glory to God.
Accepting one another brings glory to God.
When we are united and accepting one another, unbelievers will glorify God.
榮耀榮耀榮耀,彼此同心,一心一口就能夠榮耀神,
彼此去接納就能夠使榮耀同神,彼此用心,一心一口,
彼此接納就能叫人,叫未信的人去榮耀神。
This kind of church is truly a good church, a church that glorifies God.
那麼這個教會就是一個好的教會,就是一個榮耀神的教會。
See, every famous restaurant has a signature dish, right?
每一間出名的餐廳相信它都是一些招牌菜。
They are most well-known and special food.
If you go to, let's say, Michelin two-star or three-star restaurant,
the chef will proudly to say, "Hey, this is our best signature dish."
當你可能去到米芝蓮兩粒星、三粒星的餐廳,
那些廚師都很驕傲地告訴你,這個就是我們的招牌菜了。
So if I ask you, what is the signature dish of our church?
如果我問你,你覺得我們教的招牌菜是什麼呢?
Could it be the cute but noisy kid playing upstairs on level two?
你會不會覺得我們二樓樓上很吵的一班小朋友呢?
Or maybe when church lunches start again,
our laughing and delicious meal will be our signature dish.
會不會是遲些我們將會又有的愛心午飯就是我們的招牌菜呢?
Or do some of us even think that the three pastors are the signature dishes?
或者大家會不會覺得我們三位牧者就是我們的招牌菜呢?
But well, we are not that exactly young and trendy anymore.
我們也不再年輕了。
原本的翻譯是我們都已經不是小鮮肉了。
I truly believe that, my friend, every one of us,
every part of the church, we are the signature dish.
我相信大家教會的每一個肢體都是我們的招牌菜。
Each of us let others, the unbelievers,
taste the love of God and the mercy of Christ Jesus.
每一個我們的肢體裏面都被其他人去體驗到
主耶穌基督的愛和憐憫。
We all took this picture together last December.
我們去年一起拍了這張照片。
Today's Bible passage, you see, includes many names.
今天我們的經文有很多的人名出現。
They are all the people who faithfully serve God.
這些人也是一些很忠心服侍主的人。
But similarly, in our church, I would say, we also have many names.
在教會裏面,我們也有很多的人名。
We have many chains, many wongs, many phones, many trousers.
我們有姓陳,姓馮,姓何,姓趙,什麼人都有。
我們有很多不同姓氏的人。
People who open their homes together at church, together at home.
有很多頂姊妹開放他們的家庭在家裏面。
There are some people who work hard for the Lord.
他在主裏面很熱心去侍奉。
We also have people who have given up much for Jesus Christ.
同樣也有很多人為主放下很多的事情。
The point I really want to make is,
you guys are the signature dish.
今天我想說,每一個肢體都是我們教會的招牌菜。
May this message help us, each of us, become a good person.
And together, we become a good church.
That brings glory to our good Father.
願以今天的信息去幫助我們每一個人都成為一個好人,
一起去成就一個好的教會,去榮耀我們的神。
Let us pray.
我們低頭禱告。
Dear Lord, thank you for your work today.
Help us to trust you more each day.
And to live out our faith and love.
親愛的主,感謝你今天藉著你的話語對我們說話。
求你幫助我們每天去信靠你,
以愛心去活出我們的信仰。
Fill our heart with your love,
so we can care for one another with grace and kindness.
As we go, let our lives reflect your light.
求你把你的愛充滿我們的心,
使我們能夠以恩慈和憐憫彼此相待。
And in Jesus' name we pray. Amen.
求父主耶穌基督聖名之求。
阿們。